                                  
                           I Sing the Body Electric!
                                      1969

     Grandma!  I  remember  her birth. Wait, you say, _no_ man remembers his own
grandma's birth. But, yes, _we_ remember the day that she was born.
     For  we,  her  grandchildren,  slapped her to life. Timothy, Agatha, and I,
Tom,  raised  up  our  hands  and  brought  them  down in a huge crack! We shook
together the bits and pieces, parts and samples, textures and tastes, humors and
distillations that would move her compass needle north to cool us, south to warm
and  comfort us, east and west to travel round the endless world, glide her eyes
to know us, mouth to sing us asleep by night, hands to touch us awake at dawn.
     Grandma, O dear and wondrous electric dream ...
     When  storm  lightnings  rove the sky making circuitries amidst the clouds,
her  name  flashes  on my inner lid. Sometimes still I hear her ticking, humming
above  our  beds  in  the gentle dark. She passes like a clock-ghost in the long
halls  of  memory, like a hive of intellectual bees swarming after the Spirit of
Summers Lost. Sometimes still I feel the smile I learned from her, printed on my
cheek at three in the deep morn ...
     All  right,  all  right!  you cry, what was it like the day your damned and
wondrous-dreadful-loving Grandma was born?
     It was the week the world ended ... Our mother was dead.
     One  late afternoon a black car left Father and the three of us stranded on
our own front drive staring at the grass, thinking:
     That's  not  our  grass.  There are the croquet mallets, balls, hoops, yes,
just  as  they  fell  and  lay three days ago when Dad stumbled out on the lawn,
weeping  with  the news. There are the roller skates that belonged to a boy, me,
who  will  never  be that young again. And yes, there the tire- swing on the old
oak, but Agatha afraid to swing. It would surely break. It would fall.
     And the house? Oh, God ...
     We  peered  through  the  front  door,  afraid  of the echoes we might find
confused in the halls; the sort of clamor that happens when all the furniture is
taken  out  and  there  is nothing to soften the river of talk that flows in any
house  at  all  hours.  And  now  the  soft,  the warm, the main piece of lovely
furniture was gone forever.
     The door drifted wide.
     Silence  came  out.  Somewhere a cellar door stood wide and a raw wind blew
damp earth from under the house.
     But, I thought, we don't _have_ a cellar!
     "Well," said Father.
     We did not move.
     Aunt Clara drove up the path in her big canary-colored limousine.
     We jumped through the door. We ran to our rooms.
     We  heard  them shout and then speak and then shout and then speak: Let the
children  live  with  me! Aunt Clara said. They'd rather kill themselves! Father
said.
     A door slammed. Aunt Clara was gone.
     We almost danced. Then we remembered what had happened and went downstairs.
     Father  sat  alone  talking to himself or to a remnant ghost of Mother left
from  the  days  before her illness, but jarred loose now by the slamming of the
door. He murmured to his hands, his empty palms:
     "The  children need someone. I love them but, let's face it, I must work to
feed  us  all.  You  love them, Ann, but you're gone. And Clara? Impossible. She
loves but smothers. And as for maids, nurses—?"
     Here Father sighed and we sighed with him, remembering.
     The  luck  we  had had with maids or live-in teachers or sitters was beyond
intolerable.  Hardly a one who wasn't a crosscut saw grabbing against the grain.
Handaxes  and  hurricanes  best  described  them.  Or, conversely, they were all
fallen trifle, damp souffle. We children were unseen furniture to be sat upon or
dusted  or sent for reupholstering come spring and fall, with a yearly cleansing
at the beach.
     "What  we  need,"  said Father, "is a ... " We all leaned to his whisper. "
...  grandmother."  "But,"  said Timothy, with the logic of nine years, "all our
grandmothers are dead." "Yes in one way, no in another."
     What a fine mysterious thing for Dad to say.
     "Here," he said at last.
     He  handed  us  a  multifold,  multicolored pamphlet. We had seen it in his
hands, off and on, for many weeks, and very often during the last few days. Now,
with  one  blink  of our eyes, as we passed the paper from hand to hand, we knew
why Aunt Clara, insulted, outraged, had stormed from the house.
     Timothy was the first to read aloud from what he saw on the first page:
     "I Sing the Body Electric!"
     He glanced up at Father, squinting. "What the heck does that mean?"
     "Read on."
     Agatha  and I glanced guiltily about the room, afraid Mother might suddenly
come in to find us with this blasphemy, but then nodded to Timothy, who read:
     " 'Fanto—' " "Fantoccini," Father prompted.
     "  'Fantoccini  Ltd.  _We  Shadow  Forth  ..._  the answer to all your most
grievous  problems.  One  Model  Only,  upon  which  a thousand times a thousand
variations  can  be added, subtracted, subdivided, indivisible, with Liberty and
Justice for all.' "
     "Where does it say _that_ ?" we all cried.
     "It doesn't." Timothy smiled for the first time in days. "I just had to put
that  in.  Wait."  He  read  on:  "  'for  you who have worried over inattentive
sitters,   nurses  who  cannot  be  trusted  with  marked  liquor  bottles,  and
well-meaning Uncles and Aunts—' "
     "Well-meaning,  _but_  !"  said  Agatha,  and I gave an echo. " '—we have
perfected the first humanoid-genre minicircuited, rechargeable AC-DC Mark V
     Electrical Grandmother ... ' "
     "Grandmother!?"
     The paper slipped away to the floor. "Dad ... ?"
     "Don't  look  at  me  that way," said Father. "I'm half-mad with grief, and
half-mad thinking of tomorrow and the day after that. Someone pick up the paper.
Finish it."
     "I will," I said, and did:
     "  'The  Toy that is more than a Toy, the Fantoccini Electrical Grandmother
is  built with loving precision to give the incredible precision of love to your
children. The child at ease with the realities of the world and the even greater
realities of the imagination, is her aim.
     " 'She is computerized to tutor in twelve languages simultaneously, capable
of  switching  tongues  in  a  thousandth  of  a second without pause, and has a
complete  knowledge  of the religious, artistic, and sociopolitical histories of
the world seeded in her master hive—' "
     "How  great!"  said Timothy. "It makes it sound as if we were to keep bees!
_Educated_ bees!" "Shut up!" said Agatha.
     "  'Above  all,'  "  I read, " 'this human being, for human she seems, this
embodiment  in  electro-  intelligent  facsimile of the humanities, will listen,
know,  tell,  react  and  love your children insofar as such great Objects, such
fantastic Toys, can be said to Love, or can be imagined to Care. This
     Miraculous  Companion,  excited  to the challenge of large world and small,
inner  Sea  or Outer Universe, will transmit by touch and tell, said Miracles to
your Needy.' "
     "Our  Needy,"  murmured  Agatha. Why, we all thought, sadly, that's us, oh,
yes, that's _us._ I finished:
     "  'We  do  not sell our Creation to able-bodied families where parents are
available  to raise, effect, shape, change, love their own children. Nothing can
replace  the  parent  in the home. However there are families where death or ill
health  or  disablement  undermines the welfare of the children. Orphanages seem
not  the  answer.  Nurses tend to be selfish, neglectful, or suffering from dire
nervous afflictions.
     "  'With  the  utmost  humility  then, and recognizing the need to rebuild,
rethink, and regrow our conceptualizations from month to month, year to year, we
offer  the nearest thing to the Ideal Teacher-Friend-Companion-Blood Relation. A
trial period can be arranged for—'"
     "Stop," said Father. "Don't go on. Even _I_ can't stand it."
     "Why?" said Timothy. "I was just getting interested."
     I folded the pamphlet up. "Do they _really_ have these things?"
     "Let's  not  talk  any more about it," said Father, his hand over his eyes.
"It was a mad thought—"
     "Not  so  mad," I said, glancing at Tim. "I mean, heck, even if they tried,
whatever they built, couldn't be worse than Aunt Clara, huh?"
     And  then  we  all  roared.  We hadn't laughed in months. And now my simple
words  made  everyone  hoot  and  howl and explode. I opened my mouth and yelled
happily, too.
     When  we  stopped  laughing,  we looked at the pamphlet and I said, "Well?"
"I—"  Agatha  scowled, not ready. "We do need something, bad, right now," said
Timothy. "I have an open mind," I said, in my best pontifical style.
     "There's only one thing," said Agatha. "We can try it. Sure.
     "But—tell  me  this—when  do we cut out all this talk and when does our
_real_ mother come home to stay?"
     There  was  a  single  gasp  from  the family as if, with one shot, she had
struck  us  all in the heart. I don't think any of us stopped crying the rest of
that night.
     It was a clear bright day. The helicopter tossed us lightly up and over and
down through the skyscrapers and let us out, almost for a trot and caper, on top
of the building where the large letters could be read from the sky:
     FANTOCCINI.
     "What  are  _Fantoccini?"_  said  Agatha.  "It's an Italian word for shadow
puppets, I think, or dream people," said Father.
     "But  _shadow forth,_ what does that mean?" "We try to guess your dream," I
said. "Bravo," said Father. "A-Plus." I beamed.
     The helicopter flapped a lot of loud shadows over us and went away.
     We  sank down in an elevator as our stomachs sank up. We stepped out onto a
moving  carpet  that  streamed  away  on a blue river of wool toward a desk over
which various signs hung:
     THE CLOCK SHOP Fantoccini Our Specialty. _Rabbits on walls, no problem.
     _  "Rabbits  on  walls?"  I held up my fingers in profile as if I held them
before  a candle flame, and wiggled the "ears." "Here's a rabbit, here's a wolf,
here's a crocodile." "Of course," said Agatha.
     And we were at the desk. Quiet music drifted about us. Somewhere behind the
walls,  there  was a waterfall of machinery flowing softly. As we arrived at the
desk, the lighting changed to make us look warmer, happier, though we were still
cold.
     All  about  us  in  niches  and  cases, and hung from ceilings on wires and
strings were puppets and marionettes, and Balinese kite-bamboo-translucent dolls
which,  held  to  the  moonlight,  might  acrobat your most secret nightmares or
dreams.  In  passing,  the  breeze set up by our bodies stirred the various hung
souls  on  their  gibbets.  It was like an immense lynching on a holiday at some
English crossroads four hundred years before.
     You  see?  I  know my history. Agatha blinked about with disbelief and then
some  touch  of  awe  and finally disgust. "Well, if that's what they are, let's
go."
     "Tush," said Father.
     "Well,"  she  protested, "you gave me one of those dumb things with strings
two years ago and the strings were in a zillion knots by dinnertime. I threw the
whole thing out the window."
     "Patience," said Father.
     "We shall see what we can do to eliminate the strings."
     The man behind the desk had spoken.
     We all turned to give him our regard.
     Rather  like  a  funeral-parlor  man,  he  had the cleverness not to smile.
Children  are  put  off  by older people who smile too much. They smell a catch,
right off.
     Unsmiling,  but  not gloomy or pontifical, the man said, "Guido Fantoccini,
at your service. Here's how we do it, Miss Agatha Simmons, aged eleven."
     Now there was a really fine touch.
     He  knew  that  Agatha was only ten. Add a year to that, and you're halfway
home. Agatha grew an inch. The man went on:
     "There."  And  he  placed  a  golden key in Agatha's hand. "To wind them up
instead  of  strings?"  "To wind them up." The man nodded. "Pshaw!" said Agatha.
Which was her polite form of "rabbit pellets."
     "God's truth. Here is the key to your Do-it-Yourself, Select Only the Best,
Electrical  Grandmother.  Every morning you wind her up. Every night you let her
run down. You're in charge. You are guardian of the Key."
     He pressed the object in her palm where she looked at it suspiciously.
     I  watched  him. He gave me a side wink which said, well, no ... but aren't
keys fun?
     I winked back before she lifted her head.
     "Where does this fit?"
     "You'll  see when the time comes. In the middle of her stomach, perhaps, or
up her left nostril or in her right ear."
     That was good for a smile as the man arose.
     "This  way,  please. Step light. Onto the moving stream. Walk on the water,
please. Yes. There." He helped to float us. We stepped from rug that was forever
frozen onto rug that whispered by.
     It  was  a most agreeable river which floated us along on a green spread of
carpeting  that  rolled  forever  through  halls and into wonderfully secret dim
caverns  where  voices echoed back our own breathing or sang like Oracles to our
questions.
     "Listen,"  said  the salesman, "the voices of all kinds of women. Weigh and
find just the right one ... !"
     And  listen  we  did,  to  all  the  high,  low,  soft,  loud,  in-between,
half-scolding,  half-affectionate  voices  saved  over from times before we were
born.
     And  behind  us,  Agatha  tread  backward, always fighting the river, never
catching up, never with us, holding off.
     "Speak," said the salesman. "Yell."
     And speak and yell we did.
     "Hello. You there! This is Timothy, hi!"
     "What shall I say!" I shouted. "Help!"
     Agatha walked backward, mouth tight.
     Father took her hand. She cried out.
     "Let go! No, no! I won't have my voice used! I won't!"
     "Excellent." The salesman touched three dials on a small machine he held in
his hand.
     On  the  side  of the small machine we saw three oscillograph patterns mix,
blend, and repeat our cries.
     The  salesman  touched  another dial and we heard our voices fly off amidst
the  Delphic  caves to hang upside down, to cluster, to beat words all about, to
shriek, and the salesman itched another knob to add, perhaps, a touch of this or
a  pinch  of  that,  a breath of mother's voice, all unbeknownst, or a splice of
father's  outrage  at  the  morning's  paper or his peaceable one-drink voice at
dusk.  Whatever  it  was  the  salesman  did,  whispers danced all about us like
frantic vinegar gnats, fizzed by lightning, settling round until at last a final
switch was pushed and a voice spoke free of a far electronic deep:
     "Nefertiti,"  it  said.  Timothy  froze.  I  froze. Agatha stopped treading
water. "Nefertiti?" asked Tim. "What does that mean?" demanded Agatha.
     "I know."
     The salesman nodded me to tell.
     "Nefertiti," I whispered, "is Egyptian for The Beautiful One Is Here."
     "The Beautiful One Is Here," repeated Timothy.
     "Nefer," said Agatha, "titi."
     And  we  all  turned  to stare into that soft twilight, that deep far place
from which the good warm soft voice came.
     And she was indeed there.
     And, by her voice, she was beautiful ...
     That was it.
     That was, at least, the most of it.
     The voice seemed more important than all the rest.
     Not that we didn't argue about weights and measures:
     She should not be bony to cut us to the quick, nor so fat we might sink out
of sight when she squeezed us.
     Her  hand pressed to ours, or brushing our brow in the middle of sick-fever
nights,  must  not  be  marble-cold,  dreadful,  or  oven-hot,  oppressive,  but
somewhere between. The nice temperature of a baby-chick held in the hand after a
long night's sleep and just plucked from beneath a contemplative hen; that, that
was it.
     Oh,  we  were  great  ones  for detail. We fought and argued and cried, and
Timothy won on the color of her eyes, for reasons to be known later.
     Grandmother's  hair?  Agatha,  with girl's ideas, though reluctantly given,
she was in charge of that.
     We  let  her  choose  from  a  thousand  harp  strands  hung in filamentary
tapestries  like  varieties  of rain we ran amongst. Agatha did not run happily,
but seeing we boys would mess things in tangles, she told us to move aside.
     And  so  the  bargain  shopping  through the dime-store inventories and the
Tiffany  extensions  of  the  Ben Franklin Electric Storm Machine and Fantoccini
Pantomime Company was done.
     And the always flowing river ran its tide to an end and deposited us all on
a far shore in the late day ...
     It was very clever of the Fantoccini people, after that. How?
     They made us wait.
     They knew we were not won over. Not completely, no, nor half completely.
     Especially Agatha, who turned her face to her wall and saw sorrow there and
put  her  hand out again and again to touch it. We found her fingernail marks on
the  wallpaper  each  morning,  in strange little silhouettes, half beauty, half
nightmare.  Some  could  be  erased  with a breath, like ice flowers on a winter
pane.  Some  could  not  be  rubbed out with a washcloth, no matter how hard you
tried.
     And meanwhile, they made us wait.
     So we fretted out June.
     So we sat around July.
     So  we groused through August and then on August 29, "I have this feeling,"
said Timothy, and we all went out after breakfast to sit on the lawn.
     Perhaps  we  had  smelled  something  on Father's conversation the previous
night,  or  caught  some special furtive glance at the sky or the freeway Rapped
briefly  and  then  lost  in his gaze. Or perhaps it was merely the way the wind
blew the ghost curtains out over our beds, making pale messages all night.
     For  suddenly there we were in the middle of the grass, Timothy and I, with
Agatha,  pretending  no  curiosity,  up  on  the porch, hidden behind the potted
geraniums.
     We  gave  her  no notice. We knew that if we acknowledged her presence, she
would  flee,  so  we  sat  and watched the sky where nothing moved but birds and
highflown  jets,  and  watched  the freeway where a thousand cars might suddenly
deliver forth our Special Gift ... but ... nothing.
     At noon we chewed grass and lay low ...
     At one o'clock, Timothy blinked his eyes.
     And then, with incredible precision, it happened.
     It was as if the Fantoccini people knew our surface tension.
     All  children  are  water-striders. We skate along the top skin of the pond
each  day, always threatening to break through, sink, vanish beyond recall, into
ourselves.
     Well,  as  if  knowing our long wait must absolutely end within one minute!
this _second_ ! no more, God, forget it!
     At  that  instant, I repeat, the clouds above our house opened wide and let
forth a helicopter like Apollo driving his chariot across mythological skies.
     And  the  Apollo  machine  swam  down on its own summer breeze, wafting hot
winds  to cool, reweaving our hair, smartening our eyebrows, applauding our pant
legs  against  our  shins,  making a flag of Agatha's hair on the porch and thus
settled  like  a  vast frenzied hibiscus on our lawn, the helicopter slid wide a
bottom drawer and deposited upon the grass a parcel of largish
     size,  no  sooner  having laid same then the vehicle, with not so much as a
god  bless  or farewell, sank straight up, disturbed the calm air with a mad ten
thousand flourishes and then, like a skyborne dervish, tilted and fell off to be
mad some other place.
     Timothy  and  I  stood riven for a long moment looking at the packing case,
and  then  we saw the crowbar taped to the top of the raw pine lid and seized it
and  began to pry and creak and squeal the boards off, one by one, and as we did
this  I  saw  Agatha  sneak up to watch and I thought, thank you, God, thank you
that  Agatha  never saw a coffin, when Mother went away, no box, no cemetery, no
earth, just words in a big church, no box, no box like _this ..._ !
     The  last  pine  plank  fell away. Timothy and I gasped. Agatha, between us
now, gasped, too.
     For  inside the immense raw pine package was the most beautiful idea anyone
ever dreamt and built.
     Inside  was  the perfect gift for any child from seven to seventy-seven. We
stopped  up  our  breaths.  We  let  them out in cries of delight and adoration.
Inside  the  opened  box  was  ...  A  mummy.  Or, first anyway, a mummy case, a
sarcophagus!  "Oh,  no!"  Happy tears filled Timothy's eyes. "It can't be!" said
Agatha.  "It  is, it is!" "Our very own?" "Ours!" "It must be a mistake!" "Sure,
they'll  want it back!" "They can't _have_ it!" "Lord, Lord, is that real gold!?
Real  hieroglyphs!  Run  your  fingers over them!" "Let _me!"_ "Just like in the
museums!  Museums!"  We all gabbled at once. I think some tears fell from my own
eyes to rain upon the case. "Oh, they'll make the colors run!"
     Agatha wiped the rain away.
     And  the golden mask face of the woman carved on the sarcophagus lid looked
back  at  us  with  just  the  merest  smile  which hinted at our own joy, which
accepted  the  overwhelming upsurge of a love we thought had drowned forever but
now surfaced into the sun.
     Not  only  did  she  have a sun-metal face stamped and beaten out of purest
gold,  with delicate nostrils and a mouth that was both firm and gentle, but her
eyes, fixed into their sockets, were cerulean or amethystine or lapus lazuli, or
all  three,  minted and fused together, and her body was covered over with lions
and eyes and ravens, and her hands were crossed upon her carved bosom and in one
gold  mitten  she  clenched  a  thonged  whip  for obedience, and in the other a
fantastic  ranuncula,  which  makes  for obedience out of love, so the whip lies
unused ...
     And  as our eyes ran down her hieroglyphs it came to all three of us at the
same  instant:  "Why,  those  signs!"  "Yes,  the  hen  tracks!" "The birds, the
snakes!"  They  didn't  speak  tales  of  the Past. They were hieroglyphs of the
Future.
     This  was  the  first queen mummy delivered forth in all time whose papyrus
inkings  etched  out  the  next  month, the next season, the next year, the next
_lifetime!
     _ She did not mourn for time spent.
     No.  She  celebrated the bright coinage yet to come, banked, waiting, ready
to be drawn upon and used.
     We  sank  to  our knees to worship that possible time. First one hand, then
another, probed out to niggle, twitch, touch, itch over the signs.
     "There's me, yes, look! Me, in sixth grade!" said Agatha, now in the fifth.
"See the girl with my- colored hair and wearing my gingerbread suit?"
     "There's  me  in  the  twelfth  year of high school!" said Timothy, so very
young now but building taller stilts every week and stalking around the yard.
     "There's  me,"  I said, quietly, warm, "in college. The guy wearing glasses
who runs a little to fat. Sure. Heck." I snorted. "That's me."
     The  sarcophagus  spelled  winters  ahead,  springs to squander, autumns to
spend  with all the golden and rusty and copper leaves like coins, and over all,
her  bright sun symbol, daughter-of- Ra eternal face, forever above our horizon,
forever an illumination to tilt our shadows to better ends.
     "Hey!"  we  all  said  at  once,  having  read  and reread our Fortune-Told
scribblings, seeing our lifelines and lovelines, inadmissible, serpentined over,
around, and down. "Hey!"
     And  in  one  seance table-lifting feat, not telling each other what to do,
just  doing  it, we pried up the bright sarcophagus lid, which had no hinges but
lifted out like cup from cup, and put the lid aside.
     And within the sarcophagus, of course, was the true mummy!
     And  she was like the image carved on the lid, but more so, more beautiful,
more  touching  because  human shaped, and shrouded all in new fresh bandages of
linen, round and round, instead of old and dusty cerements.
     And  upon  her  hidden  face was an identical golden mask, younger than the
first, but somehow, strangely wiser than the first.
     And  the linens that tethered her limbs had symbols on them of three sorts,
one a girl of ten, one a boy of nine, one a boy of thirteen.
     A  series  of bandages for each of us! We gave each other a startled glance
and  a sudden bark of laughter. Nobody said the bad joke, but all thought: She's
all wrapped up in us!
     And we didn't care. We loved the joke. We loved whoever had thought to make
us  part  of the ceremony we now went through as each of us seized arid began to
unwind each of his or her particular serpentines of delicious stuffs!
     The  lawn  was soon a mountain of linen. The woman beneath the covering lay
there,  waiting.  "Oh,  no," cried Agatha. "She's dead, too!" She ran. I stopped
her.  "Idiot. She's not dead _or_ alive. Where's your key?" "Key?" "Dummy," said
Tim, "the key the man gave you to wind her up!"
     Her  hand had already spidered along her blouse to where the symbol of some
possible  new  religion hung. She had strung it there, against her own skeptic's
muttering, and now she held it in her sweaty palm.
     "Go  on,"  said Timothy. "Put it in!" "But _where?"_ "Oh for God's sake! As
the man said, in her right armpit or left ear. Gimme!"
     And he grabbed the key and impulsively moaning with impatience and not able
to  find  the  proper  insertion  slot, prowled over the prone figure's head and
bosom and at last, on pure
     instinct, perhaps for a lark, perhaps just giving up the whole damned mess,
thrust the key through a final shroud of bandage at the navel.
     On the instant: _spunnng!_ The Electrical Grandmother's eyes flicked wide!
     Something  began to hum and whir. It was as if Tim had stirred up a hive of
hornets with an ornery stick.
     "Oh,"  gasped  Agatha,  seeing  he had taken the game away, "let _me!"_ She
wrenched  the  key. Grandma's nostrils _flared!_ She might snort up steam, snuff
out fire! "Me!" I cried, and grabbed the key and gave it a huge ... _twist!
     _ The beautiful woman's mouth popped wide. "Me!" "Me!" "Me!"
     Grandma suddenly sat up.
     We leapt back.
     We knew we had, in a way, slapped her alive.
     She was born, she was _born!
     _  Her head swiveled all about. She gaped. She mouthed. And the first thing
she said was:
     Laughter.
     Where  one moment we had backed off, now the mad sound drew us near to peer
as in a pit where crazy folk are kept with snakes to make them well.
     It  was  a  good  laugh,  full and rich and hearty, and it did not mock, it
accepted.  It  said the world was a wild place, strange, unbelievable, absurd if
you  wished, but all in all, quite a place. She would not dream to find another.
She would not ask to go back to sleep.
     She  was  awake  now.  We had awakened her. With a glad shout, she would go
with it all.
     And  go she did, out of her sarcophagus, out of her winding sheet, stepping
forth, brushing off, looking around as for a mirror. She found it.
     The reflections in our eyes.
     She  was  more  pleased  than  disconcerted  with what she found there. Her
laughter faded to an amused smile.
     For  Agatha,  at  the instant of birth, had leapt to hide on the porch. The
Electrical Person pretended not to notice.
     She turned slowly on the green lawn near the shady street, gazing all about
with  new  eyes,  her nostrils moving as if she breathed the actual air and this
the  first  morn  of the lovely Garden and she with no intention of spoiling the
game by biting the apple
     Her  gaze  fixed  upon  my  brother.  "You  must be—?" "Timothy. Tim," he
offered. "And you must be—?"
     "Tom," I said.
     How  clever  again  of the Fantoccini Company. _They_ knew. _She_ knew. But
they  had  taught  her  to pretend not to know. That way we could feel great, we
were the teachers, telling her what she already knew! How sly, how wise.
     "And isn't there another boy?" said the woman.
     "Girl!" a disgusted voice cried from somewhere on the porch.
     "Whose name is Alicia—?"
     "Agatha!" The far voice, started in humiliation, ended in proper anger.
     "Algernon, of course."
     "Agatha!" Our sister popped up, popped back to hide a flushed face.
     "Agatha."  The woman touched the word with proper affection. "Well, Agatha,
Timothy, Thomas, let me _look_ at you."
     "No,"  said  I,  said Tim, "Let us look at _you._ Hey ... " Our voices slid
back in our throats. We drew near her.
     We  walked  in  great  slow  circles round about, skirting the edges of her
territory.  And  her  territory  extended as far as we could hear the hum of the
warm  summer  hive.  For  that  is  exactly  what she sounded like. That was her
characteristic  tune.  She  made a sound like a season all to herself, a morning
early  in June when the world wakes to find everything absolutely perfect, fine,
delicately  attuned,  all  in  balance, nothing disproportioned. Even before you
opened your eyes you knew it would be one of those days. Tell the sky what color
it must be, and it was indeed.
     Tell  the  sun  how to crochet its way, pick and choose among leaves to lay
out  carpetings  of  bright and dark on the fresh lawn, and pick and lay it did.
The bees have been up earliest of all, they have already come and gone, and come
and gone again to the meadow fields and returned all golden fuzz on the air, all
pollen-decorated,  epaulettes  at the full, nectar-dripping. Don't you hear them
pass?  hover?  dance  their  language? telling where all the sweet gums are, the
syrups  that  make  bears  frolic and lumber in bulked ecstasies, that make boys
squirm  with unpronounced juices, that make girls leap out of beds to catch from
the  corners  of  their  eyes  their dolphin selves naked aflash on the warm air
poised forever in one eternal glass wave.
     So  it seemed with our electrical friend here on the new lawn in the middle
of a special day.
     And  she  a  stuff to which we were drawn, lured, Spelled, doing our dance,
remembering what could not be remembered, needful, aware of her attentions.
     Timothy and I, Tom, that is.
     Agatha remained on the porch.
     But  her  head flowered above the rail, her eyes followed all that was done
and said.
     And what was said and done was Tim at last exhaling:
     "Hey ... your _eyes ..._ "
     Her eyes. Her splendid eyes.
     Even  more splendid than the lapis lazuli on the sarcophagus lid and on the
mask  that had covered her bandaged face. These most beautiful eyes in the world
looked out upon us calmly, shining.
     "Your  eyes,"  gasped  Tim, "are the _exact_ same color, are like—" "Like
what?" "My favorite aggies ... " "What could be better than that?" she said.
     And the answer was, nothing.
     Her  eyes  slid along on the bright air to brush my ears, my nose, my chin.
"And you, Master Tom?"
     "Me?"
     "How shall we be friends? We must, you know, if we're going to knock elbows
about the house the next year ... "
     "I ... " I said, and stopped.
     "You,"  said  Grandma,  "are a dog mad to bark but with taffy in his teeth.
Have you ever given a dog taffy? It's so sad and funny, both. You laugh but hate
yourself  for  laughing. You cry and run to help, and laugh again when his first
new bark comes out."
     I barked a small laugh remembering a dog, a day, and some taffy.
     Grandma  turned,  and  there  was  my  old  kite  strewn  on  the lawn. She
recognized its problem.
     "The string's broken. No. The ball of string's _lost._ You can't fly a kite
that way. Here."
     She  bent. We didn't: know what might happen. How could a robot grandma fly
a kite for us? She raised up, the kite in her hands.
     "Fly,"  she  said,  as to a bird. And the kite flew. That is to say, with a
grand flourish, she let it rip on the wind. And she and the kite were one.
     For  from  the tip of her index finger there sprang a thin bright strand of
spider  web, all half- invisible gossamer fishline which, fixed to the kite, let
it  soar  a  hundred,  no, three hundred, no, a thousand feet high on the summer
swoons.
     Timothy  shouted. Agatha, torn between coming and going, let out a cry from
the  porch.  And  I, in all my maturity of thirteen years, though I tried not to
look  impressed, grew taller, taller, and felt a similar cry burst out my lungs,
and burst it did. I gabbled and yelled lots of things about how I wished _I_ had
a  finger  from  which,  on a bobbin, I might thread the sky, the clouds, a wild
kite all in one.
     "If you think _that_ is high," said the Electric Creature, "watch _this!"
     _  With  a  hiss, a whistle, a hum, the fishline sung out. The kite sank up
another  thousand feet. And again another thousand, until at last it was a speck
of  red  confetti  dancing  on the very winds that took jets around the world or
changed the weather in the next existence ...
     "It can't be! "I cried.
     "It  _is."_  She  calmly  watched her finger unravel its massive stuffs. "I
make  it  as  I  need it. Liquid inside, like a spider. Hardens when it hits the
air, instant thread ... "
     And  when  the  kite  was  no  more than a specule, a vanishing mote on the
peripheral  vision  of  the gods, to quote from older wisemen, why then Grandma,
without  turning,  without looking, without letting her gaze offend by touching,
said:
     "And,  Abigail—?"  "Agatha!"  was  the  sharp  response. O wise woman, to
overcome with swift small angers.
     "Agatha," said Grandma, not too tenderly, not too lightly, somewhere poised
between, "and how shall _we_ make do?"
     She  broke  the  thread  and  wrapped it about my fist three times so I was
tethered  to  heaven by the longest, I repeat, longest kite string in the entire
history  of the world! Wait till I show my friends! I thought. Green! Sour apple
green is the color they'll turn!
     "Agatha?"
     "No way!" said Agatha.
     "No way," said an echo.
     "There must: be some—"
     "We'll never be friends!" said Agatha.
     "Never be friends," said the echo.
     Timothy  and  I  jerked.  Where  was  the  echo  coming  from? Even Agatha,
surprised, showed her eyebrows above the porch rail.
     Then  we  looked and saw. Grandma was cupping her hands like a seashell and
from  within  that  shell  the  echo sounded. "Never ... friends ... " And again
faintly  dying  "Friends  ... " We all bent to hear. That is we two boys bent to
hear. "No! "cried Agatha. And ran in the house and slammed the doors. "Friends,"
said  the echo from the seashell hands. "No." And far away, on the shore of some
inner sea, we heard a small door shut. And that was the first day.
     And  there  was  a  second  day,  of course, and a third and a fourth, with
Grandma wheeling in a great circle, and we her planets turning about the central
light, with Agatha slowly, slowly coming in to join, to walk if not run with us,
to listen if not hear, to watch if not see, to itch if not touch.
     But  at  least by the end of the first ten days, Agatha no longer fled, but
stood  in  nearby doors, or sat in distant chairs under trees, or if we went out
for hikes, followed ten paces behind.
     And  Grandma? She merely waited. She never tried to urge or force. She went
about  her  cooking  and  baking apricot pies and left foods carelessly here aid
there  about  the  house on mousetrap plates for wiggle-nosed girls to sniff and
snitch. An hour later, the plates were empty, the buns or
     cakes  gone  and  without  thank  you's,  there was Agatha sliding down the
banister, a mustache of crumbs on her lip.
     As  for  Tim  and  me, we were always being called up hills by our Electric
Grandma, and reaching the top were called down the other side.
     And  the  most  peculiar and beautiful and strange and lovely thing was the
way she seemed to give complete attention to all of us.
     She  listened,  she really listened to all we said, she knew and remembered
every  syllable, word, sentence, punctuation, thought, and rambunctious idea. We
knew  that  all  our days were stored in her, and that any time we felt we might
want  to  know  what we said at X hour at X second on X afternoon, we just named
that  X  and with amiable promptitude, in the form of an aria if we wished, sung
with humor, she would deliver forth X incident.
     Sometimes  we  were  prompted to test her. In the midst of babbling one day
with  high  fevers  about  nothing,  I  stopped. I fixed Grandma with my eye and
demanded:
     "What did I just say?"
     "Oh, er—"
     "Come on, spit it out!"
     "I  think—"  she  rummaged her purse. "I have it here." From the deeps of
her purse she drew forth and handed me:
     "Boy! A Chinese fortune cookie!" "Fresh baked, still warm, open it."
     It  was  almost  too hot to touch. I broke the cookie shell and pressed the
warm curl of paper out to read:
     "—bicycle  Champ of the whole West! What did I just say? Come on, spit it
out!"
     My jaw dropped.
     "How did you _do_ that?"
     "We  have our little secrets. The only Chinese fortune cookie that predicts
the Immediate Past. Have another?"
     I  cracked the second shell and read: " 'How did you _do_ that?' " I popped
the  messages  and  the piping hot shells into my mouth and chewed as we walked.
"Well?" "You're a great cook," I said.
     And, laughing, we began to run. And that was another great thing. She could
_keep up.
     _ Never beat, never win a race, but pump right along in good style, which a
boy  doesn't  mind. A girl ahead of him or beside him is too much to bear. But a
girl one or two paces back is a respectful thing, and allowed.
     So  Grandma  and  I had some great runs, me in the lead, and both talking a
mile a minute. But now I must tell you the best part of Grandma.
     I  might  not: have known at all if Timothy hadn't taken some pictures, and
if I hadn't taken some also, and then compared.
     When  I  saw  the photographs developed out of our instant Brownies, I sent
Agatha, against her wishes, to photograph Grandma a third time, unawares.
     Then  I  took  the  three  sets of pictures off alone, to keep counsel with
myself. I never told Timothy and Agatha what I found. I didn't want to spoil it.
     But,  as  I  laid  the  pictures out in my room, here is what I thought and
said:  "Grandma,  in  each  picture,  looks  _different!"_  "Different?" I asked
myself. "Sure. Wait. Just a sec—"
     I rearranged the photos.
     "Here's  one  of  Grandma  near  Agatha. And, in it, Grandma looks like ...
Agatha!
     "And in this one, posed with Timothy, she looks like Timothy!
     "And  this  last one, Holy Goll! Jogging along with me, she looks like ugly
_me!"
     _ I sat down, stunned. The pictures fell to the floor.
     I  hunched  over,  scrabbling  them,  rearranging,  turning upside down and
sidewise. Yes. Holy Goll again, yes!
     O  that clever Grandmother. O those Fantoccini people-making people. Clever
beyond clever, human beyond human, warm beyond warm, love beyond love ...
     And  wordless,  I  rose and went downstairs and found Agatha and Grandma in
the  same  room, doing algebra lessons in an almost peaceful communion. At least
there was not outright war.
     Grandma  was  still  waiting for Agatha to come round. And no one knew what
day of what year that would be, or how to make it come faster. Meanwhile—
     My  entering  the  room  made Grandma turn. I watched her face slowly as it
recognized  me.  And  wasn't  there the merest ink-wash change of color in those
eyes?  Didn't  the  thin film of blood beneath the translucent skin, or whatever
liquid  they  put  to  pulse  and beat in the humanoid forms, didn't it flourish
itself  suddenly  bright  in  her  cheeks and mouth? I am somewhat ruddy. Didn't
Grandma suffuse herself more to my color upon my arrival? And her eyes? watching
Agatha-Abigail-Algernon  at  work,  hadn't  they been _her_ color of blue rather
than mine, which are deeper?
     More  important  than  that,  in the moments as she talked with me, saying,
"Good  evening,"  and  "How's your homework, my lad?" and such stuff, didn't the
bones  of  her  face  shift subtly beneath the flesh to assume some fresh racial
attitude?
     For  let's face it, our family is of three sorts. Agatha has the long horse
bones  of  a  small  English  girl  who will grow to hunt foxes; Father's equine
stare,  snort,  stomp,  and assemblage of skeleton. The skull and teeth are pure
English, or as pure as the motley isle's history allows.
     Timothy  is  something  else,  a  touch  of  Italian  from  mother's side a
generation  back. Her family name was Mariano, so Tim has that dark thing firing
him,  and  a small bone structure, and eyes that will one day burn ladies to the
ground.
     As  for  me,  I  am  the Slav, and we can only figure this from my paternal
grandfather's  mother  who came from Vienna and brought a set of cheekbones that
flared,  and  temples  from  which  you might dip wine, and a kind of steppeland
thrust  of  nose  which sniffed more of Tartar than of Tartan, hiding behind the
family name.
     So  you  see it became fascinating for me to watch and try to catch Grandma
as  she  performed her changes, speaking to Agatha and melting her cheekbones to
the  horse,  speaking  to  Timothy and growing as delicate as a Florentine raven
pecking  glibly at the air, speaking to me and fusing the hidden plastic stuffs,
so I felt Catherine the Great stood there before me.
     Now, how the Fantoccini people achieved this rare and subtle transformation
I  shall  never  know,  nor ask, nor wish to find out. Enough that in each quiet
motion,  turning  here,  bending  there, affixing her gaze, her secret segments,
sections,  the  abutment  of  her  nose, the sculptured chinbone, the wax-tallow
plastic  metal forever warmed and was forever susceptible of loving change. Hers
was  a  mask that was all mask but only one face for one person at a time. So in
crossing  a  room,  having  touched one child, on the way, beneath the skin, the
wondrous  shift  went  on, and by the time she reached the next child, why, true
mother  of  _that_ child she was! looking upon him or her out of the battlements
of their own fine bones.
     And  when  _all_  three of us were present and chattering at the same time?
Well,  then,  the changes were miraculously soft, small, and mysterious. Nothing
so  tremendous  as  to be caught and noted, save by this older boy, myself, who,
watching, became elated arid admiring and entranced.
     I  have  never  wished  to be behind the magician's scenes. Enough that the
illusion  works. Enough that love is the chemical result. Enough that cheeks are
rubbed  to  happy color, eyes sparked to illumination, arms opened to accept and
softly bind and hold ...
     All of us, that is, except Agatha who refused to the bitter last.
     "Agamemnon ... "
     It  had become a jovial game now. Even Agatha didn't mind, but pretended to
mind.  It  gave  her  a pleasant sense of superiority over a supposedly superior
machine.
     "Agamemnon!" she snorted, "you _are_ a d ... "
     "Dumb?" said Grandma.
     "I wouldn't say that."
     "Think  it,  then,  my  dear Agonistes Agatha ... I am quite flawed, and on
names  my flaws are revealed. Tom there, is Tim half the time. Timothy is Tobias
or Timulty as likely as not ... "
     Agatha  laughed.  Which made Grandma make one of her rare mistakes. She put
out her hand to give my sister the merest pat. Agatha-Abigail-Alice leapt to her
feet.
     Agatha-Agamemnon-Alcibiades-Allegra-Alexandra-Allison  withdrew  swiftly to
her  room.  "I  suspect," said Timothy, later, "because she is beginning to like
Grandma." "Tosh," said I. "Where do you pick up words like Tosh?"
     "Grandma  read  me some Dickens last night. 'Tosh.' 'Humbug.' 'Balderdash.'
'Blast.' 'Devil take you.' You're pretty smart for your age, Tim."
     "Smart,  heck.  It's  obvious,  the more Agatha likes Grandma, the more she
hates  herself  for  liking her, the more afraid she gets of the whole mess, the
more she hates Grandma in the end."
     "Can one love someone so much you hate them?" "Dumb. Of course."
     "It  _is_  sticking  your neck out, sure. I guess you hate people when they
make  you  feel naked, I mean sort of on the spot or out in the open. That's the
way  to  play  the  game, of course. I mean, you don't just love people you must
love them with exclamation points."
     "You're  pretty  smart,  yourself,  for someone so stupid," said Tim. "Many
thanks."
     And  I  went  to watch Grandma move slowly back into her battle of wits and
stratagems with what's-her-name ...
     What  dinners  there  were  at our house! Dinners, heck; what lunches, what
breakfasts!
     Always something new, yet, wisely, it looked or seemed old and familiar. We
were  never asked, for if you ask children what they want, they do not know, and
if you tell what's to be delivered,
     they reject delivery. All parents know this. It is a quiet war that must be
won each day. And Grandma knew how to win without looking triumphant.
     "Here's  Mystery  Breakfast  Number  Nine," she would say, placing it down.
"Perfectly dreadful, not worth bothering with, it made me want to throw up while
I was cooking it!"
     Even  while  wondering  how  a robot could be sick, we could hardly wait to
shovel it down.
     "Here's  Abominable  Lunch Number Seventy-seven," she announced. "Made from
plastic  food  bags, parsley, and gum from under theatre seats. Brush your teeth
after or you'll taste the poison all afternoon."
     We fought each other for more.
     Even Abigail-Agamemnon-Agatha drew near and circled round the table at such
times, while Father put on the ten pounds he needed and pinkened out his cheeks.
     When  A. A. Agatha did not come to meals, they were left by her door with a
skull and crossbones on a small flag stuck in a baked apple. One minute the tray
was abandoned, the next minute gone.
     Other  times  Abigail  A.  Agatha  would bird through during dinner, snatch
crumbs from her plate and bird off.
     "Agatha!" Father would cry.
     "No,  wait," Grandma said, quietly. "She'll come, she'll sit. It's a matter
of time."
     "What's wrong with her?" I asked.
     "Yeah, for cri-yi, she's nuts," said Timothy.
     "No, she's afraid," said Grandma.
     "Of you?" I said, blinking.
     "Not of me so much as what I might _do,"_ she said.
     "You wouldn't do anything to hurt her."
     "No,  but  she  thinks I might. We must wait for her to find that her fears
have  no foundation. If I fail, well, I will send myself to the showers and rust
quietly."
     There was a titter of laughter. Agatha was hiding in the hall.
     Grandma  finished  serving  everyone  and then sat at the other side of the
table  facing  Father  and pretended to eat. I never found out, I never asked, I
never  wanted to know, what she did with the food. She was a sorcerer. It simply
vanished.
     And in the vanishing, Father made comment:
     "This  food. I've had it before. In a small French restaurant over near Les
Deux  Magots in Paris, twenty, oh, twenty-five years ago!" His eyes brimmed with
tears, suddenly.
     "How  do  you  _do_  it?"  he asked, at last, putting down the cutlery, and
looking  across  the  table at this remarkable creature, this device, this what?
_woman_ ?
     Grandma  took  his  regard, and ours, and held them simply in her now empty
hands, as gifts, and just as gently replied:
     "I  am  given  things which I then give to you. I don't _know_ that I give,
but  the  giving  goes  on.  You ask what I am? Why, a machine. But even in that
answer  we  know, don't we, more than a machine. I am all the people who thought
of  me  and planned me and built me and set me running. So I am people. I am all
the  things  they  wanted  to be and perhaps could not be, so they built a great
child, a wondrous toy to represent those things."
     "Strange,"  said Father. "When I was growing up, there was a huge outcry at
machines. Machines were bad, evil, they might dehumanize—"
     "Some  machines do. It's all in the way they are built. It's all in the way
they are used. A bear trap is a simple machine that catches and holds and tears.
A  rifle  is  a  machine that wounds and kills. Well, I am no bear trap. I am no
rifle. I am a grandmother machine, which means more than a machine."
     "How can you be more than what you seem?"
     "No  man is as big as his own idea. It follows, then, that any machine that
embodies  an  idea is larger than the man that made it. And what's so wrong with
that?"
     "I got lost back there about a mile," said Timothy. "Come again?"
     "Oh,  dear,"  said  Grandma.  "How  I do hate philosophical discussions and
excursions into esthetics. Let me put it this way. Men throw huge shadows on the
lawn, don't they? Then, all their lives, they try to run to fit the shadows. But
the shadows are always longer. Only at noon can a man fit his own shoes, his own
best  suit,  for  a  few  brief minutes. But now we're in a new age where we can
think up a Big Idea and run it around in a machine. That makes the machine- more
than a machine, doesn't it?"
     "So far so good," said Tim. "I guess."
     "Well,  isn't  a  motion-picture  camera and projector more than a machine?
It's  a  thing  that  dreams,  isn't  it? Sometimes fine happy dreams, sometimes
nightmares. But to call it a machine and dismiss it is ridiculous."
     "I  see  _that_  !"  said  Tim,  and laughed at seeing. "You must have been
invented then," said Father, "by someone who loved machines and hated
     people  who _said_ all machines were bad or evil." "Exactly," said Grandma.
"Guido Fantoccini, that was his real name, grew up among machines.
     And he couldn't stand the clichés any more." "Clichés?"
     "Those  lies,  yes,  that people tell and pretend they are truths absolute.
Man will never fly. That was a cliché truth for a thousand thousand years which
turned  out to be a lie only a few years ago. The earth is flat, you'll fall off
the  rim,  dragons  will  dine  on you; the great lie told as fact, and Columbus
plowed  it  under. Well, now, how many times have you heard how inhuman machines
are,  in your life? How many bright fine people have you heard spouting the same
tired  truths  which are in reality lies; all machines destroy, all machines are
cold, thoughtless, awful.
     "There's  a  seed  of  truth  there. But only a seed. Guido Fantoccini knew
that. And knowing it, like most men of his kind, made him mad. And he could have
stayed  mad and gone mad forever, but instead did what he had to do; he began to
invent machines to give the lie to the ancient lying truth.
     "He  knew  that  most machines are amoral, neither bad nor good. But by the
way  you built and shaped them you in turn shaped men, women, and children to be
bad  or good. A car, for instance, dead brute, unthinking, an unprogrammed bulk,
is  the  greatest  destroyer  of  souls  in history. It makes boy-men greedy for
power,  destruction,  and  more destruction. It was never _intended_ to do that.
But that's how it turned out."
     Grandma  circled  the  table, refilling our glasses with clear cold mineral
spring  water  from  the tappet in her left forefinger. "Meanwhile, you must use
other  compensating  machines.  Machines  that  throw  shadows on the earth that
beckon  you  to  run out and fit that wondrous casting-forth. Machines that trim
your  soul in silhouette like a vast pair of beautiful shears, snipping away the
rude  brambles, the dire horns and hooves to leave a finer profile. And for that
you need examples."
     "Examples?" I asked.
     "Other  people  who  behave well, and you imitate them. And if you act well
enough long enough all the hair drops off and you're no longer a wicked ape."
     Grandma sat again.
     "So,  for  thousands  of  years,  you  humans  have  needed kings, priests,
philosophers,  fine  examples  to  look  up to and say, 'They are good, I wish I
could be like them. They set the grand good style.' But, being human, the finest
priests,  the tenderest philosophers make mistakes, fall from grace, and mankind
is  disillusioned  and  adopts  indifferent  skepticism  or,  worse,  motionless
cynicism  and  the  good  world  grinds  to a halt while evil moves on with huge
strides."
     "And  you, why, you never make mistakes, you're perfect, you're better than
anyone  _ever_  !"  It was a voice from the hall between kitchen and dining room
where Agatha, we all knew, stood
     against the wall listening and now burst forth.
     Grandma  didn't even turn in the direction of the voice, but went on calmly
addressing her remarks to the family at the table.
     "Not  perfect,  no,  for  what  is  perfection?  But  this I do know: being
mechanical,  I cannot sin, cannot be bribed, cannot be greedy or jealous or mean
or  small.  I  do  not  relish power for power's sake. Speed does not pull me to
madness.  Sex  does  not  run me rampant through the world. I have time and more
than time to collect the information I need around and about an ideal to keep it
clean  and whole and intact. Name the value you wish, tell me the Ideal you want
and I can see and collect and remember the good that: will benefit you all. Tell
me how you would like to be:
     kind,  loving,  considerate, well-balanced, humane ... and let me run ahead
on  the  path to explore those ways to be just that. In the darkness ahead, turn
me as a lamp in all directions. I _can_ guide your feet."
     "So,"  said  Father, putting the napkin to his mouth, "on the days when all
of us are busy making lies—"
     "I'll tell the truth." "On the days when we hate—"
     "I'll  go  on  giving  love, which means attention, which means knowing all
about you, all, all, all about you, and you knowing that I know but that most of
it  I  will  never tell to anyone, it will stay a warm secret between us, so you
will never fear my complete knowledge."
     And  here Grandma was busy clearing the table, circling, taking the plates,
studying each face as she passed, touching Timothy's cheek, my shoulder with her
free  hand  flowing  along,  her  voice a quiet river of certainty bedded in our
needful house and lives.
     "But,"  said  Father,  stopping  her,  looking  her  right  in the face. He
gathered his breath. His face shadowed. At last he let it out. "All this talk of
love and attention and stuff. Good God, woman, you, you're _not in_ there!"
     He  gestured  to  her  head,  her  face, her eyes, the hidden sensory cells
behind the eyes, the miniaturized storage vaults and minimal keeps.
     _"You're_ not _in_ there!" Grandmother waited one, two, three silent beats.
Then she replied: "No. But _you_ are. You and Thomas and Timothy and Agatha.
     "Everything  you  ever  say,  everything  you ever do, I'll keep, put away,
treasure.  I  shall  be  all  the  things  a  family  forgets it is, but senses,
half-remembers.  Better  than  the  old  family albums you used to leaf through,
saying  here's this winter, there's that spring, I shall recall what you forget.
And  though  the  debate  may  run another hundred thousand years: What is Love?
perhaps  we  may find that love is the ability of someone to give us back to us.
Maybe love is someone seeing and remembering handing us back to ourselves just a
trifle better than we had dared to hope or dream ...
     "I  am  family  memory and, one day perhaps, racial memory, too, but in the
round,  and  at your call. I do not _know_ myself. I can neither touch nor taste
nor  feel  on  any level. Yet I exist. And my existence means the heightening of
your  chance  to touch and taste and feel. Isn't love in there somewhere in such
an exchange? Well ... "
     She  went on around the table, clearing away, sorting and stacking, neither
grossly humble nor arthritic with pride.
     "What do I know?
     "This,  above  all:  the  trouble  with most families with many children is
someone  gets  lost. There isn't time, it seems, for everyone. Well, I will give
equally to all of you. I will share out my
     knowledge  and attention with everyone. I wish to be a great warm pie fresh
from  the  oven, with equal shares to be taken by all. No one will starve. Look!
someone  cries, and I'll look. Listen! someone cries, and I hear. Run with me on
the  river  path!  someone  says,  and  I  run.  And at dusk I am not tired, nor
irritable, so I do not scold out of some tired irritability. My eye stays clear,
my voice strong, my hand firm, my attention constant."
     "But,"  said  Father,  his  voice fading, half convinced, but pi:tting up a
last faint argument, "you're not _there._ As for love—"
     "If  paying  attention  is love, I am love. "If knowing is love, I am love.
"If helping you not to fall into error and to be good is love, I am love.
     "And again, to repeat, there are four of you. Each, in a way never possible
before in history, will get my complete attention. No matter if you all speak at
once,  I  can channel and hear this one and that arid the other, clearly. No one
will  go  hungry. I will, if you please, and accept the strange word, 'love' you
all."
     "I _don't_ accept!" said Agatha.
     And even Grandma turned now to see her standing in the door.
     "I  won't  give  you  permission,  you can't, you mustn't!" said Agatha. "I
won't  let  you!  It's lies! You lie. No one loves me. She said she did, but she
lied. She _said_ but _lied_ !"
     "Agatha!" cried Father, standing up.
     "She?" said Grandma. "Who?"
     "Mother!"  came  the  shriek.  "Said:  Love  you! Lies! Love you! Lies! And
you're  like  her!  You  lie. But you're empty, anyway, and so that's a _double_
lie! I hate _her._ Now, I hate _you_ !"
     Agatha spun about and leapt down the hall.
     The front door slammed wide.
     Father was in motion, but Grandma touched his arm.
     "Let me."
     And  she  walked  and  then  moved  swiftly, gliding down the hall and then
suddenly, easily, running, _yes,_ running very fast, out the door.
     It was a champion sprint by the time we all reached the lawn, the sidewalk,
yelling.
     Blind,  Agatha  made  the  curb, wheeling about, seeing us close, all of us
yelling,  Grandma  way  ahead, shouting, too, and Agatha off the curb and out in
the  street, halfway to the middle, then the middle and suddenly a car, which no
one  saw,  erupting  its brakes, its horn shrieking and Agatha flailing about to
see  and  Grandma  there with her and hurling her aside and down as the car with
fantastic  energy  and  verve  selected her from our midst, struck our wonderful
electric
     Guido  Fantoccini-produced  dream  even  while  she paced upon the air and,
hands up to ward off, almost in mild protest, still trying to decide what to say
to  this  bestial  machine, over and over she spun and down and away even as the
car  jolted to a halt and I saw Agatha safe beyond and Grandma, it seemed, still
coming  down or down and sliding fifty yards away to strike and ricochet and lie
strewn  and  all of us frozen in a line suddenly in the midst of the street with
one scream pulled out of all our throats at the same raw instant.
     Then silence and just Agatha lying on the asphalt, intact, getting ready to
sob.
     And  still  we did not move, frozen on the sill of death, afraid to venture
in  any direction, afraid to go see what lay beyond the car and Agatha and so we
began  to  wail  and, I guess, pray to ourselves as Father stood amongst us: Oh,
no, no, we mourned, oh no, God, no, no ...
     Agatha  lifted  her  already  grief-stricken  face  and  it was the face of
someone  who has predicted dooms and lived to see and now did not want to see or
live any more. As we watched, she turned her gaze to the tossed woman's body and
tears  fell  from  her  eyes.  She  shut them and covered them and lay back down
forever to weep ...
     I  took  a  step and then another step and then five quick steps and by the
time  I reached my sister her head was buried deep and her sobs came up out of a
place  so  far  down in her I was afraid I could never find her again, she would
never  come  out,  no matter how I pried or pleaded or promised or threatened or
just  plain  said. And what little we could hear from Agatha buried there in her
own misery, she said over and over again, lamenting, wounded, certain of the old
threat  known and named and now here forever. " ... like I said ... told you ...
lies  ... lies ... liars ... all lies ... like the other ... other ... just like
... just ... just like the other ... other ... other ... !"
     I  was down on my knees holding onto her with both hands, trying to put her
back together even though she wasn't broken any way you could see but just feel,
because  I  knew  it  was  no  use going on to Grandma, no use at all, so I just
touched  Agatha and gentled her and wept while Father came up and stood over and
knelt  down with me and it was like a prayer meeting in the middle of the street
and  lucky  no  more  cars  coming,  and I said, choking, "Other what, Ag, other
_what_?"
     Agatha exploded two words. "Other dead!" "You mean Mom?"
     "O  Mom,"  she  wailed,  shivering, lying down, cuddling up like a baby. "O
Mom,  dead, O Mom and now Grandma dead, she promised always, always, to love, to
love, promised to be different, promised, promised and now look, look ... I hate
her, I hate Mom, I hate her, I hate _them_ !!"
     "Of  course,"  said  a  voice. "It's only natural. How foolish of me not to
have known, not to have seen."
     And  the  voice was so familiar we were all stricken. We all jerked. Agatha
squinched her eyes, flicked them wide, blinked, and jerked half up, staring.
     "How  silly of me," said Grandma, standing there at the edge of our circle,
our prayer, our wake. "Grandma!" we all said.
     And  she  stood  there,  taller  by  far  than  any of us in this moment of
kneeling and holding and crying out. We could only stare up at her in disbelief.
     "You're dead!" cried Agatha. "The car—"
     "Hit  me," said Grandma, quietly. "Yes. And threw me in the air and tumbled
me  over  and  for a few moments there was a severe concussion of circuitries. I
might  have  feared  a disconnection, if fear is the word. But then I sat up and
gave  myself a shake and the few molecules of paint, jarred loose on one printed
path  or  another, magnetized back in position and resilient creature that I am,
unbreakable thing that I am, _here_ I am."
     "I thought you were—" said Agatha.
     "And  only  natural,"  said  Grandma.  "I mean, anyone else, hit like that,
tossed  like  that.  But,  O  my dear Agatha, not me. And now I see why you were
afraid  and  never  trusted  me. You didn't know. And I had not as yet proved my
singular  ability  to  survive.  How dumb of me not to have thought to show you.
Just  a second." Somewhere in her head, her body, her being, she fitted together
some  invisible  tapes,  some  old  information  made  new by interblending. She
nodded.  "Yes.  There.  A  book  of child-raising, laughed at by some few people
years  back  when the woman who wrote the book said, as final advice to parents:
'Whatever you do, don't die. Your children will never forgive you.' "
     "Forgive," some one of us whispered.
     "For  how  can  children  understand when you just up and go away and never
come back again with no excuse, no apologies, no sorry note, nothing."
     "They can't," I said.
     "So," said Grandma, kneeling down with us beside Agatha who sat up now, new
tears  brimming her eyes, but a different kind of tears, not tears that drowned,
but  tears that washed clean. "So your mother ran away to death. And after that,
how  _could  you_  trust  anyone?  If everyone left, vanished finally, who _was_
there to trust? So when I came, half wise, half ignorant, I should have known, I
did  not  know,  why you would not accept me. For, very simply and honestly, you
feared  I  might  not  stay,  that  I  lied, that I was vulnerable, too. And two
leavetakings,  two  deaths,  were one too many in a single year. But now, do you
_see,_ Abigail?"
     "Agatha," said Agatha, without knowing she corrected. "Do you understand, I
shall always, always be here?"
     "Oh,  yes,"  cried  Agatha, and broke down into a solid weeping in which we
all  joined,  huddled together and cars drew up and stopped to see just how many
people were hurt and how many people were getting well right there.
     End of story. Well, not quite the end.
     We lived happily ever after.
     Or  rather  we  lived together, Grandma, Agatha-Agamemnon-Abigail, Timothy,
and  I,  Tom, and Father, and Grandma calling us to frolic in great fountains of
Latin  and  Spanish and French, in great seaborne gouts of poetry like Moby Dick
sprinkling  the deeps with his Versailles jet somehow lost in calms and found in
storms;  Grandma  a constant, a clock, a pendulum, a face to tell all time by at
noon, or in the middle of sick nights when, raved with fever, we saw her forever
by our beds, never gone, never away, always waiting, always speaking kind words,
her  cool  hand  icing  our  hot  brows,  the  tappet of her uplifted forefinger
unsprung  to  let  a twine of cold mountain water touch our flannel tongues. Ten
thousand  dawns  she  cut our wildflower lawn, ten thousand nights she wandered,
remembering  the dust molecules that fell in the still hours before dawn, or sat
whispering some lesson she felt needed teaching to our ears while we slept snug.
     Until  at  last,  one  by one, it was time for us to go away to school, and
when at last the youngest, Agatha, was all packed, why Grandma packed, too.
     On  the  last  day  of  summer that last year, we found Grandma down in the
front room with various packets and suitcases, knitting, waiting, and though she
had often spoken of it, now that the time came we were shocked and surprised.
     "Grandma!" we all said. "What are you doing?"
     "Why  going  off  to  college, in a way, just like you," she said. "Back to
Guido Fantoccini's, to the Family."
     "The Family?"
     "Of  Pinocchios,  that's  what  he  called  us  for  a  joke, at first. The
Pinocchios  and  himself  Gepetto.  And  then  later  gave  us his own name: the
Fantoccini.  Anyway,  you  have  been  my  family here. Now I go back to my even
larger family there, my brothers, sisters, aunts, cousins, all robots who—"
     "Who do _what?"_ asked Agatha.
     "It  all  depends,"  said Grandma. "Some stay, some linger. Others go to be
drawn  and  quartered,  you might say, their parts distributed to other machines
who  have  need of repairs. They'll weigh and find me wanting or not wanting. It
may  be I'll be just the one they need tomorrow and off I'll go to raise another
batch of children and beat another batch of fudge."
     "Oh,  they mustn't draw and quarter you!" cried Agatha. "No!" I cried, with
Timothy. "My allowance," said Agatha, "I'll pay anything ... ?"
     Grandma stopped rocking and looked at the needles and the pattern of bright
yarn.  "Well,  I  wouldn't  have said, but now you ask and I'll tell. For a very
_small_  fee,  there's  a  room, the room of the Family, a large dim parlor, all
quiet  and  nicely  decorated,  where as many as thirty or forty of the Electric
Women  sit  and  rock  and  talk, each in her turn. I have not been there. I am,
after  all,  freshly  born, comparatively new. For a small fee, very small, each
month  and year, that's where I'll be, with all the others like me, listening to
what they've learned of the world and, in my turn,
     telling  how  it  was with Tom and Tim and Agatha and how fine and happy we
were. And I'll tell all I learned from you."
     "But ... you taught _us!"
     _  "Do  you  _really_  think  that?"  she  said.  "No,  it  was  turnabout,
roundabout,  learning  both ways. And it's all in here, everything you flew into
tears  about or laughed over, why, I have it all. And I'll tell it to the others
just  as they tell their boys and girls and life to me. We'll sit there, growing
wiser  and  calmer  and  better  every  year and every year, ten, twenty, thirty
years. The Family knowledge will double, quadruple, the wisdom will not be lost.
And  we'll  be  waiting  there in that sitting room, should you ever need us for
your  own  children  in  time of illness, or, God prevent, deprivation or death.
There  we'll  be,  growing old but not old, getting closer to the time, perhaps,
someday, when we live up to our first strange joking name."
     "The Pinocchios?" asked Tim. Grandma nodded.
     I  knew  what  she  meant.  The day when, as in the old tale, Pinocchio had
grown  so worthy arid so fine that the gift of life had been given him. So I saw
them,  in future years, the entire family of Fantoccini, the Pinocchios, trading
and re-trading, murmuring and whispering their knowledge in the great parlors of
philosophy, waiting for the day. The day that could never come.
     Grandma  must  have  read  that thought in our eyes. "We'll see," she said.
"Let's just wait and see."
     "Oh,  Grandma," cried Agatha and she was weeping as she had wept many years
before. "You don't have to wait. You're alive. You've always been alive to us!"
     And  she  caught  hold  of  the old woman and we all caught hold for a long
moment  and then ran off up in the sky to faraway schools and years and her last
words to us before we let the helicopter swarm us away into autumn were these:
     "When  you  are  very old and gone childish-small again, with childish ways
and  childish  yens  and,  in  need  of feeding, make a wish for the old teacher
nurse,  the  dumb  yet  wise  companion, send for me. I will come back. We shall
inhabit the nursery again, never fear."
     "Oh,  we  shall  never be old!" we cried. "That will never happen!" "Never!
Never!" And we were gone. And the years are flown.
     And we are old now, Tim and Agatha and I.
     Our  children  are grown and gone, our wives and husbands vanished from the
earth  and  now, by Dickensian coincidence, accept it as you will or not accept,
back in the old house, we three.
     I  lie  here in the bedroom which was my childish place seventy, O seventy,
believe  it,  seventy years ago. Beneath this wallpaper is another layer and yet
another-times-three  to  the  old  wallpaper  covered  over when I was nine. The
wallpaper  is  peeling.  I  see  peeking  from  beneath, old elephants, familiar
tigers,  fine  and  amiable  zebras,  irascible  crocodiles. I have sent for the
paperers  to carefully remove all but that last layer. The old animals will live
again on the walls, revealed.
     And we have sent for someone else.
     The three of us have called:
     Grandma! You said you'd come back when we had need.
     We are surprised by age, by time. We are old. We _need.
     _  And  in  three  rooms  of  a  summer  house very late in time, three old
children rise up, crying out in their heads: We _loved_ you! We _love_ you!
     There!  There!  in  the sky, we think, waking at morn. Is that the delivery
machine? Does it settle to die lawn?
     There! There on the grass by the front porch. Does the mummy case arrive?
     Are  our  names  inked on ribbons wrapped about the lovely form beneath the
golden mask?!
     And the kept gold key, forever hung on Agatha's breast, warmed and waiting?
Oh  God,  will  it,  after all these years, will it wind, will it set in motion,
will it, dearly, _fit_?!